California Federation of Chaparral Poets
California Federation of Chaparral Poets(CFCP)Records
1943-2013
1990-2012 bulk
CFCP1
California Federation of Chaparral Poets
12 record cartons, 12 cubic feet.
California Federation of Chaparral Poets PO Box 1161 Modesto, CA 95353-1161
The California Federation of Chaparral Poets, Inc. (CFCP) records reflect the administration and events of CFCP, one of the oldest and largest organizations in the world that supports and encourages the creation and celebration of poetry. The collection contains the minutes of their Board, annual convention programs, contest publications and member publications. Their annual poetry contests, conventions and publications are filled with the best of California poetry and the poetry of the world.
Administrative Information
A copy of this collection guide is located in an unnumbered folder at the front of Box 1.
Access:
Collection is open for research with no restrictions.
Accruals:
Additional materials may be added to this collection as donations are received.
Additional Materials:
Related collections of materials are housed at Glendale, CA Public Library as well as the California State Library in Sacramento, CA.
Organization:
The collection is organized in 15 series, with subseries or file subarrangements where appropriate.
Series I.
Board of Directors records
Series II.
Brochure and Related Artwork
Series III.
By-Laws and Articles of Incorporation
Series IV.
California State Library
Series V.
Chapters
Series VI.
Contests
Series VII.
Conventions
Series VIII.
Correspondence
Series IX.
Administrative and Subject Files
Series X.
Allied Poetry Organizations
Series XI.
Treasurer records
Series XII.
Chaparral newsletter – “Chaparral Updrafts”
Series XIII.
Assorted CFCP and CFCP Chapter Books and Pamphlets
Series XIV.
CFCP Member Publications
Series XV.
Oversize Materials
History of the California Federation of Chaparral Poets, Inc.
The story of Chaparral began in 1939 when the city of Glendale organized its First Annual Festival of Arts. The Poetry Committee’s display included a brochure, “In the Chaparral.”
On February 9, 1940, the Glendale Poetry Chapter was formed, followed in March by the Pasadena Poetry Club. From these two groups CFCP was organized.
The first convention was held in 1940 at the Glendale YWCA, with more than 300 attending. By January 1942, the Federation had grown to 11 Chapters across southern California, and continued to experience steady growth throughout the state.
By 1963, when the convention was held in Sacramento, CFCP had become the largest poetry group in the world, with 30 chapters from both northern and southern California, as well as members from more than a dozen other states. Since then, the convention generally alternates between northern and southern host Chapters. It presently has 19 active Chapters.
The Name
Symbolically the name ‘Chaparral’ was chosen because it is typically Californian, as the low growth of chaparral that covers the hillsides and desert wastes of California, adding beauty and fragrance to barren countrysides, might be applied to poetry singing its way into a war-torn and barren world today.
—from the program of the Third Annual Convention, held in May, 1942 in Hollywood
Source: CFCP website: http://www.chaparralpoets.org/history.html
Controlled Access Headings:
Library of Congress Subject Headings:
Personal and Corporate Names:
California Federation of Chaparral Poets; Wilson, Katharine Margaret
General Subjects:
California--Poetry.; Poetry, English--20th century.; Poetry, Modern--Congresses.
Bibliography
More information may be found about CFCP in the following publication:
California Federation of Chaparral Poets (2012). Chaparral Updrafts. Modesto: California Federation of Chaparral Poets
Container List
Box and Folder numbers in bold.
- Board of Directors records, I: (Box 1, Folder 52 folders)
  Scope and Content:
  This series contains job descriptions of organization officers, all meeting minutes as well as records of all meetings, both in person and online.
  - Job Descriptions (Folder 1)
  - Board Correspondence (Folder 2)
  - Meetings: (Folder 3-4)
    - 2013 (Folder 3)
    - 2012 (Folder 4)
- Brochure and Related Artwork, II: (Box 1, Folder 52 folders)
  This series contains materials related to the promotional/informational brochure, including the artwork used for the publication
  - Brochure and Related Artwork (Folder 31)
- By-laws and Articles of Incorporation, III: (Box 1, Folder 52 folders)
  This series contains copies of organizational By-Laws and records pertaining to incorporation of the CFCP.
  - By-laws (Folder 32)
  - Incorporation Papers (Folder 33)
- California State Library, IV: (Box 1)
  This series contains records pertaining to the California State Library, the planned deposit of the CFCP Archives to the California State Library and related information
  - California State Library correspondence and information (Folder 34)
- Chapters, V: (Box 1, Folder 52 folders)
  This series contains records pertaining to both past and present Chapters of the CFCP, including newsletters, membership rosters and other administrative and poetry activities. Records have been separated into separate folders for those Chapters that have enough records to merit this treatment. For all other chapters where minimal records are available, they have been collated alphabetically.
  Return to Organization
  - Chapter - Alameda Island, Aeolian, Alpha (Folder 35)
  - Chapter - Robert Frost (Folder 43)
    - Membership: (Folder 44, 45)
      - 2001-2013 (Folder 44)
      - 1999-2000 (Folder 45)
    - Contest 1997 (Folder 46)
  - Chapter - Poets of the Vineyard (Folder 47)
    - Membership materials (Folder 48)
    - newsletters (Folder 49)
- Contests, VI: (Box 2, Folder 59 folders)
  This series encompasses all available materials regarding annual contest planning, advertising, and entries. It does not include publications, which are gathered with other publications in Series XII.
  - 2013 (Folder 1)
  - 2012 (Folder 2)
- Conventions, VII: (Box 2, Folder 59 folders)
  This series contains pertinent records and available copies of programs for the annual CFCP convention.
  - Convention - undated (Folder 26)
  - 2013 (Folder 27)
  - 2012 (Folder 28)
- Correspondence, VIII: (Box 3, Folder 29 folders)
  This series contains all correspondence of a general nature not directly related to other series in this collection.
  - Correspondence - undated (Folder 1)
  - 2013 (Folder 2)
- Administrative and Subject Files, IX: (Box 3, Folder 29 folders)
  This series contains general administrative and subject files. Please see folder titles for specific content descriptions.
  - History (Folder 14)
  - Members: Memorials (Folder 15)
- Allied Poetry Organizations, X: (Box 3, Folder 29 folders)
  This series contains This series contains materials from allied poetry organizations, some of which share members with CFCP.
  - Berkeley Poets' Dinner programs (Folder 25)
    - Dancing Poetry Festival (Folder 26-27)
      - 2010- (Folder 26)
      - 1998-2009 (Folder 27)
- Assorted CFCP and CFCP Chapter Books and Pamphlets, XIII: (Box 7)
  This series consists of all CFCP and cFCP Chapter Publications except Convention Programs, which are filed with their annual Convention materials under Series VII. Manuals or scrapbooks are not included.
  - Adult Poetry Competition, A:
    This subseries consists of all available Adult Poetry Contest winner publications. The name of the publication varies over the years. Titles have been taken directly from publication.
    - Prize Winning and Honorable Mention Poems - 1965 California Poetry Competition, Sponsored by CFCP (Folder 1)
    - Wings of Pegasus - 1966 California Poetry Competition, Sponsored by CFCP (Folder 2)
    - Prizewinning Poems: (Folder 40-47)
      - 1986
      - 1987
      - 1988
      - 1989
      - 1990
      - 1991
      - 1992
      - 1993
  - Youth Competition, B:
    This subseries consists of all available Youth Contest winner publications. The name of the publication varies over the years. Titles have been taken directly from publication.
    - Winning poems - high school contests, 1971 California Poetry Competition (Folder 1)
    - Winners, Junior and Senior High School Contest (Folder 2-4)
      - 1974
      - 1975
      - 1976
  - CFCP Publications, C:
    - The Chaparral Poet - May 1976
    - The Chaparral Poet - April 1977
- CFCP Member Publications, XIV: (Box 8)
  This series consists of individual publications by member poets or publications in which CFCP member poets' work appear.
  Angilly, Richard
  Wind Music
  Cole, Eddie-Lou
  Strange 1972.
  Eddie-Lou Cole was a Chaparral poet for many years and a member of the Tumbleweed Chapter. Her work has been featured in many poetry publications and anthologies around the world. Some of these journals and her poems are listed here for your convenience:
  Ekphrasis: A Poetry Journal
  Gusto
  Haiku Journal
  Spring Blossoms, 1990
  Daughters of Eve, 2003
  Lines in the Sand
  Unforgivin, 2001
  The Door Ajar, 2008